A Finding Aid to the Charles Pollock Papers, 1875-1994, in the Archives of American Art AAA.pollchar
Archives of American Art
Charles Pollock papers
1875-1994
AAA.pollchar
Archives of American Art
3.1 Linear feet
The papers of painter, muralist, and educator Charles Pollock measure 3.1 linear feet and date from 1875 to 1994. Found within the papers are biographical materials; family and personal correspondence; subject files on art and professional topics; writings; printed material; artwork, including political cartoons and figurative sketches; and photographs of Pollock, his family and friends, and his work.
Pollock, Charles C.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The papers were donated in 1975 by Pollock's first wife, Elizabeth Feinberg Pollock, with assistance from Charles Pollock on the selection of items. Additional materials were donated in 1988 by his second wife, Sylvia Winter Pollock. From 1991 to 1994, Elizabeth Pollock gifted additional correspondence and photographs to the Archives.
Separated Materials note
Nine works of art included in the 1975 gift from Elizabeth Pollock were transferred to the Smithsonian American Art Museum, formerly the National Collection of Fine Arts, in 1976.
Related Archival Materials note
Also found in the Archives of American Art are the Elizabeth Feinberg Pollock memoirs and the Jackson Pollock and Lee Krasner papers.
Existence and Location of Copies note
Portions of this collection are available on legacy 35 mm microfilm reels 1097, 1116, and 4213-4215 at the Archives of American Art offices, and through interlibrary loan. Researchers should note that the microfilm does not represent the entire collection and the arrangement of the papers as described in this finding aid does not reflect the order of the collection on microfilm due to reprocessing.
Conditions Governing Access note
Use of original papers requires an appointment and is limited to the Archives' Washington, D.C. Research Center. Contact Reference Services for more information.
Biographical/Historical note
Painter, muralist, and educator Charles Pollock (1902-1988) lived and worked in East Lansing, Michigan, New York City, Detroit, and Paris, France and painted in a social realist style early in his career before transitioning to abstract works in the 1940s. He is also the eldest brother of the abstract expressionist Jackson Pollock.
Born in Denver, Colorado to Stella McClure and LeRoy Pollock, Pollock received his early art training at the Otis Institute in Los Angeles, California. In 1926, he moved to New York City to attend the Art Students League where he studied under Thomas Hart Benton, with whom Jackson also studied after joining Charles in New York in 1930. In New York, he met and married his first wife, Elizabeth Feinberg Pollock, in 1931.
Pollock moved to Washington, D.C. in 1935 to work for the Resettlement Administration, and after two years, accepted a position as the political illustrator for the United Automobile Workers' newspaper in Detroit. After a short stint as the illustrator and layout editor for the paper, Pollock served as the supervisor of the Michigan WPA Mural Painting and Graphic Arts division from 1938 to 1942.
Upon completion of a three panel mural for Michigan State University in 1942, Pollock was invited to join the faculty of the art department, where he taught lettering, printmaking, typography, and design. During his twenty-five year tenure at the University, he also served as a book designer for the University's Press and continued to develop his abstract painting style. He met and married his second wife, Sylvia Winter Pollock, in 1957. Pollock served as the University of Pennsylvania's artist in residence in 1965 and 1967, and was the recipient of a National Foundation of Arts Grant (1967) and a Guggenheim Grant (1967-1968). The Pollocks moved to Paris in 1970, where Charles died of complications from a stroke in 1988.
Scope and Contents note
The papers of painter, muralist, and educator Charles Pollock measure 3.1 linear feet and date from 1875 to 1994. Found within the papers are biographical materials; family and personal correspondence; subject files on art and professional topics; writings; printed material; artwork, including political cartoons and figurative sketches; and photographs of Pollock, his family and friends, and his work.
Arrangement note
The collection is arranged as 7 series.
Series 1: Biographical Materials, 1945-1988 (7 folders; Box 1)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1927-1994 (1 linear foot; Boxes 1-2)
Series 3: Subject Files, 1931-1988 (0.8 linear feet; Box 2)
Series 4: Writings, 1935-1965 (2 folders; Box 2)
Series 5: Printed Material, 1930-1990 (4 folders; Box 2)
Series 6: Artwork, 1925-1949 (0.7 linear feet; Box 3, OV 5-8)
Series 7: Photographic Materials, 1875-1987 (0.4 linear feet; Boxes 3-4)
Pollock, Jackson, 1912-1956; Art teachers--France; Art teachers--Michigan; Art teachers--New York (State)--New York; Cartoons (humorous images); Expatriate painters--France--Paris; Muralists--France--Paris; Muralists--Michigan; Muralists--New York (State)--New York; Painters--France--Paris; Painters--Michigan; Painters--New York (State)--New York; Photographs; Sketches
- Biographical Materials, 1945-1988; Series 1; 7 Folders Box 1
  Arrangement note
  Materials are arranged by document type.
  Scope and Contents note
  Biographical materials include autobiographical summaries, a Pollock family tree, a chronology of events in Pollock's life, employment related correspondence, and a transcript of a 1979 interview with Paul Sporn concerning the Federal Art Project in Michigan.
  - Autobiographical Material, circa 1970-1985 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Chronology, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Employment, circa 1945-1965 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Employment, University of Pennsylvania, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Family Tree, circa 1988 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Grants and Fellowships, circa 1950-1970 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Interview Transcript, with Paul Sporn, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Correspondence, 1927-1994; Series 2; 1 Linear feet Boxes 1-2
  Correspondence is arranged as two subseries, family and general. Family correspondence includes substantial letters from Charles Pollock to his first wife, Elizabeth Feinberg Pollock, and incoming letters from his mother, Stella Pollock. There are also letters from Charles's brothers, Frank, Sanford, Marvin Jay, and Jackson, as well as from extended aunts and uncles, and his second wife, Sylvia Winter Pollock. Letters to Elizabeth include scholarly inquiries regarding both Charles and Jackson Pollock.
  General correspondence consists of letters to Charles Pollock regarding the exhibition, commission, and sales of his artwork, as well as correspondence from friends, colleagues, and scholarly researchers. Correspondents include musicologist Charles Seeger and Thomas Hart Benton, with whom he met during his time at the Resettlement Administration and the Art Students League respectively.
  Correspondence from Jackson Pollock and Thomas Hart Benton were gifted as photocopies only.
  The series is arranged as 2 subseries. Letters are arranged chronologically by recipient.
  2.1: Family, 1929-1994
  2.2: General, 1927-1988
  - Family, 1929-1994; 2.1
    - Charles Pollock to Elizabeth F. Pollock, 1929-1986 (Box 1, Folder 8-18)
    - Charles Pollock to Mr. Feinberg (Elizabeth's father), 1931 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Elizabeth F. Pollock to Charles Pollock, 1929-1974 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Elizabeth F. Pollock to Stella Pollock (mother-in-law), 1931-1956 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Elizabeth F. Pollock to Pollock Family, 1981-1994 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - To Elizabeth F. Pollock, Regarding Charles Pollock, 1965-1990 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - To Elizabeth F. Pollock, Regarding Jackson Pollock, 1965-1994 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - To Elizabeth F. Pollock, Others, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Charles Pollock to Stella Pollock (mother), 1944 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Stella Pollock to Charles and Frank Pollock, circa 1929-1931 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Stella Pollock to Charles Pollock and Others, 1931-1933 (Box 1, Folder 28-29)
    - Stella Pollock to Charles Pollock and Elizabeth Pollock, circa 1930-1950 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Stella Pollock to Charles Pollock and Elizabeth Pollock, 1936-1937 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Stella Pollock to Charles Pollock and and Family, 1938-1956 (Box 1, Folder 32-40)
    - To Stella Pollock, from Family and Friends, circa 1930-1956 (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - Stella Pollock, Last Illness, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - Frank Pollock to Charles Pollock and Others, circa 1933-1958 (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - Jackson Pollock to Charles Pollock and Others, circa 1929-1944 (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - Marvin Jay Pollock to Charles Pollock and Others, circa 1931-1964 (Box 1, Folder 45)
    - Sanford ("Sande") Pollock to Charles Pollock and Others, circa 1933-1961 (Box 1, Folder 46)
    - Mary Keicher, Les McClure, and Rose Miller to Charles Pollock and Family, 1960-1979 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - General, 1927-1988; 2.2
    - A-L, circa 1930-1965 (Box 1, Folder 48)
    - M-Z, circa 1930-1965 (Box 1, Folder 49)
    - Benton, Thomas Hart and Rita, 1927-1975 (Box 1, Folder 50)
    - Hayden, William, circa 1929-1930 (Box 1, Folder 51)
    - Huberman, Leo, circa 1935-1938 (Box 1, Folder 52)
    - Resettlement Administration, 1935-1937 (Box 1, Folder 53)
    - Seeger, Charles, circa 1939-1952 (Box 1, Folder 54)
    - Letters of Inquiry, 1977-1986 (Box 1, Folder 55)
    - Letters of Inquiry, O'Connor, Francis, 1963-1978 (Box 2, Folder 1-2)
    - Letters of Inquiry, Potter, Jeffrey, 1982-1986 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Letters of Inquiry, Regarding Jackson Pollock, 1963-1988 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Subject Files, 1931-1988; Series 3; 0.8 Linear feet Box 2
  Subject files are on calligraphy and printing, Pollock's personal exhibition files, and Michigan State University print design projects. The exhibition files contain correspondence with galleries as well as exhibition announcements and catalogs. Files on Michigan State design projects include correspondence, book jackets, stationary samples, and final class projects designed by Pollock's students.
  Materials are arranged by subject and document type.
  - Calligraphy and Printing (Box 2)
    - Correspondence, 1944-1967 (Box 2, Folder 5-7)
    - Design and Printing, circa 1945-1965 (Box 2, Folder 8-9)
    - Emulsions and Media, circa 1945-1965 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Charles Pollock Exhibitions (Box 2)
    - Correspondence, 1931-1985 (Box 2, Folder 11-15)
    - Dayton Art Institute, 1969-1972 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Gertrude Kasle Gallery, 1965-1969 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Henri Gallery, 1966-1970 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Lists, Forms, and Invitations, circa 1936-1947 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Clippings, 1955-1988 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1936-1988 (Box 2, Folder 21-22)
  - Michigan State University (Box 2)
    - Correspondence, 1945-1954 (Box 2, Folder 23-25)
    - Pollock Murals, circa 1952 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Research Grant, 1966-1967 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Designs, circa 1949-1951 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Designs, Book Jackets, circa 1945-1955 (Box 2, Folder 29-30)
    - Design Projects by Pollock Students, circa 1945-1955 (Box 2, Folder 31-32)
- Writings, 1935-1965; Series 4; 2 Folders Box 2
  Writings consists of lists, notes, and speech fragments by Pollock and an undated typescript of a memoir by Jellyroll Morton.
  - Notes, Lists, Speeches, and Etc., circa 1935-1965 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Memoir, by Jellyroll Morton (typescript), circa 1935-1965 (Box 2, Folder 34)
- Printed Material, 1930-1990; Series 5; 4 Folders Box 2
  Printed material includes a chapbook of poems, These Intensities, by Sylvia Pollock and illustrated by Charles Pollock. There are also magazines and copies of United Automobile Worker newspapers from 1937-1938.
  - Chapbook, These Intensities by Sylvia and Charles Pollock, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Clippings, 1930, 1984-1990 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Periodicals, Magazines, 1936, 1977, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Periodicals, U.A.W. Newspapers, 1937-1938 (Box 2, Folder 38)
- Artwork, 1925-1949; Series 6; 0.7 Linear feet Box 3, OV 5-8
  Artwork consists of etchings, a sketchbook, loose sketches, and political cartoons. Political cartoons include original oversize renderings and prints depicting U.A.W. labor disputes. Sketches are rendered in pen and ink, graphite, and watercolor and include figure studies of family and labor workers. The sketchbook also contains music scores for Thomas Hart Benton's amateur harmonica group.
  - Etchings, circa 1948-1949 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Political Illustrations, Originals, circa 1935-1940 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    Oversized material housed in OV 5-8.
  - Political Illustrations, Prints, circa 1935-1940 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    Oversized material housed in OV 7.
  - Sketchbook, circa 1930 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Sketches, Loose, circa 1925-1933 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Oversize Political Illustrations (originals) from Box 3, Folder 2, circa 1935-1940 (Box OV 5-8)
  - Oversize Political Illustrations (prints) from Box 3, Folder 3, circa 1935-1940 (Box OV 7)
  - Oversize Loose Sketches from Box 3, Folder 5, circa 1925-1933 (Box OV 7)
- Photographic Materials, 1875-1987; Series 7; 0.4 Linear feet Boxes 3-4
  Photographic materials include 48 numbered photos from a Pollock family album that includes Pollock's parents, brothers, wife, daughter, and various extended family members and friends. Additional photographs depict Pollock family members, artist friends, including Frank Goeritz, and Arthur Millier, and reproductions of artwork.
  Materials from the album are ordered numerically as arranged by the donor. Other photographs are arranged by subject.
  - Photographs of Charles Pollock and Family (#1-20), 1904-1937 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Photographs of Charles Pollock and Family (#21-48), 1938-1975 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Photographs of Charles Pollock and Family, circa 1875-1960 (Box 3, Folder 8-9)
    Oversized material housed in Box 4, Folder 1.
  - Photographs of Charles, Elizabeth F., and Jeremy Pollock, circa 1930-1941 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Photographs of Charles Pollock, Frank Goeritz, and Arthur Millier, circa 1922-1923 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Photographs of Charles Pollock and Others, circa 1938-1987 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    Oversized material housed in Box 4, Folder 2.
  - Photographs of Friends, circa 1920-1935 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Photographs of Artwork, circa 1940-1960 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Oversized Photographs of Charles Pollock and Family from Box 3, Folders 8 and 12, circa 1905-1965 (Box 4, Folder 1-2)